<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.3 20210610//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-3-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.3"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.6.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art560.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.6.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_SCOG100266 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?FILEgr1 jpg ?><?FILEgr2 jpg ?><?properties open_access?><processing-meta base-tagset="archiving" mathml-version="3.0" table-model="xhtml" tagset-family="jats"><restricted-by>pmc</restricted-by></processing-meta><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Schizophr Res Cogn</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Schizophr Res Cogn</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Schizophrenia Research: Cognition</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2215-0013</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">9361330</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2215-0013(22)00031-2</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scog.2022.100266</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">100266</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Paper</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Cognitive and perceptual impairments in schizophrenia extend to other psychotic disorders but not schizotypy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0005"><name><surname>Frattaroli</surname><given-names>Natalie</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0010"><name><surname>Geljic</surname><given-names>Mia</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0015"><name><surname>Runkowska</surname><given-names>Dominika</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="fn0005" ref-type="fn">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0020"><name><surname>Darke</surname><given-names>Hayley</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0025"><name><surname>Reddyhough</surname><given-names>Caitlin</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0030"><name><surname>Mills</surname><given-names>Taylor</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0035"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>Matthew</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0040"><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>Rachel</given-names></name><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0045"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>Olivia</given-names></name><xref rid="af0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="au0050"><name><surname>Sundram</surname><given-names>Suresh</given-names></name><email>Suresh.sundram@monash.edu</email><xref rid="af0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="af0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref><xref rid="cr0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib><aff id="af0005"><label>a</label>Department of Psychiatry, School of Clinical Sciences, Monash University. Level 3 P-Block, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road, Clayton, Victoria 3168, Australia</aff><aff id="af0010"><label>b</label>Melbourne School of Psychological Sciences, Redmond Barry Building, Faculty of Medicine, Dentistry and Health Sciences, University of Melbourne, VIC 3010, Australia</aff><aff id="af0015"><label>c</label>Mental Health Program, Monash Health, Level 3 P-Block, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road, Clayton, Victoria 3168, Australia</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cr0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author at: Department of Psychiatry, School of Clinical Sciences, Monash University, Level 3 P-Block, Monash Medical Centre, 246 Clayton Road, Clayton, Victoria, Australia. <email>Suresh.sundram@monash.edu</email></corresp><fn id="fn0005"><label>1</label><p id="np0015">These authors contributed equally to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>05</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>8</month><year>2022</year></pub-date><volume>30</volume><elocation-id>100266</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>3</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>22</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>25</day><month>7</month><year>2022</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2022 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2022</copyright-year><license><ali:license_ref xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" specific-use="textmining" content-type="ccbyncndlicense">https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ali:license_ref><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="ab0005"><p>Well characterised cognitive and perceptual impairments in schizophrenia may not be diagnostically specific with some studies suggesting no significant differences between psychotic disorders. This transdiagnostic ambiguity is paralleled in the boundary distinctions between psychotic disorders and the sub-threshold symptomatology of schizotypy. The current study used the CNTRACS test battery to explore if performance deficits in visual integration, relational memory and goal maintenance were specific to schizophrenia or extend to other psychotic disorders; and if task performance varied between individuals with schizophrenia and schizotypy in healthy adults. The sample consisted of healthy controls, and patients who met DSM-IV criteria for schizophrenia, other psychotic disorders and non-psychotic disorders who were tested in person; and an online sample of self-assessed healthy adults. No significant differences were found in performance between patients with schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders in contrast to non-psychotic disorders and healthy controls. The high schizotypy group performed better on the tasks compared to the other psychoses and schizophrenia groups. There were no differences in the healthy control group between individuals with high versus low schizotypy or between in-person and online task performance. These findings support the notion that cognitive and perceptual impairments in schizophrenia extend to other psychotic disorders but are discontinuous with schizotypy. This study provides insights into similarities between schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders with regards to the potential neural substrates underpinning these functions and supports the use of online tools for assessing domains of cognition and perception.</p></abstract><abstract abstract-type="author-highlights" id="ab0010"><title>Highlights</title><p><list list-type="simple" id="l0005"><list-item id="li0005"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0005">Cognitive and perceptual task performance is similar between schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0010"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0010">Cognitive and perceptual task performance in schizotypy is different to schizophrenia.</p></list-item><list-item id="li0015"><label>&#x02022;</label><p id="p0015">Online versions of the JOVI, RiSE and DPX tasks were comparable to in-person administration.</p></list-item></list></p></abstract><kwd-group id="ks0005"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Schizophrenia</kwd><kwd>Psychosis</kwd><kwd>Schizotypy</kwd><kwd>Visual integration</kwd><kwd>Relational memory</kwd><kwd>Goal maintenance</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s0005"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p id="p0020">Schizophrenia is a disorder characterised by extensive cognitive and perceptual impairments (<xref rid="bb0090" ref-type="bibr">McCleery and Nuechterlein, 2019</xref>; <xref rid="bb0140" ref-type="bibr">Sheffield et al., 2018</xref>) including visual integration, relational encoding and retrieval, and goal maintenance domains. These are relevant to functional outcomes in schizophrenia (<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Barch et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bb0060" ref-type="bibr">Green, 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bb0115" ref-type="bibr">Ragland et al., 2009</xref>; <xref rid="bb0175" ref-type="bibr">Wells et al., 2015</xref>) and have all been demonstrably linked to neural systems (<xref rid="bb0095" ref-type="bibr">Mukherjee et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Poppe et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0150" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Tripathi et al., 2018</xref>) providing opportunity for translational research (<xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr">Barch et al., 2009</xref>).</p><p id="p0025">However, the diagnostic specificity of these findings is not well resolved and the limited literature comparing visual integration, relational memory and goal maintenance performance across different psychiatric illnesses, suggests that individuals with psychotic disorders do not significantly differ in task performance. For example, <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Owoso et al. (2013)</xref> found no major quantitative differences between schizophrenia and schizoaffective patient groups in these three domains with both uniformly performing worse than healthy controls. Likewise, <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Smucny et al. (2020)</xref> concluded that impaired visual integration performance was not specific to schizophrenia but also present in bipolar I and schizoaffective disorders. This is consistent with transdiagnostic ambiguity in cognitive and perceptual domains between psychotic disorders (<xref rid="bb0035" ref-type="bibr">East-Richard et al., 2020</xref>).</p><p id="p0030">To assist in the disambiguation of cognition and perception between schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders relatively specific tasks for cognitive and perceptual domains were identified by the Cognitive Neuroscience Treatment Research to Improve Cognition in Schizophrenia project (CNTRICS; <xref rid="bb0020" ref-type="bibr">Carter and Barch, 2007</xref>) and more recently, the CNTRACS (Cognitive Neuroscience Test Reliability and Clinical Applications for Schizophrenia; <xref rid="bb0045" ref-type="bibr">Gold, 2012</xref>) consortium. With regards to visual integration, relational encoding and retrieval, and goal maintenance, the Jittered Orientation Visual Integration (JOVI), Relational and item-Specific Encoding (RiSE) and the Dot Pattern Expectancy (DPX) tasks were respectively designated as useful measures for these domains. The JOVI, RiSE and DPX lack significant inter-correlation (<xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Gold et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Smucny et al., 2020</xref>) indicating three distinctive domains of cognition and perception. These tasks have proven psychometric characteristics as well as good construct validity (<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Ragland et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2012</xref>) and are well tolerated by patients.</p><p id="p0035">Using the JOVI, RiSE and DPX tasks, previous studies have repeatedly demonstrated significant impairments in schizophrenia spectrum participants compared to healthy controls (<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0075" ref-type="bibr">Keane et al., 2014</xref>; <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr">Poppe et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0125" ref-type="bibr">Ragland et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al., 2010</xref>; <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Barch et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr">Cohen et al., 1999</xref>). These findings add support to claims that these tasks provide valid and sensitive measures of impaired cognitive and perceptual function specific to schizophrenia (<xref rid="bb0080" ref-type="bibr">Lopez-Garcia et al., 2016</xref>; <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Ragland et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2012</xref>).</p><p id="p0040">Therefore, the diagnostic specificity remains unresolved with existing data conflicted about deficits overlapping with other disorders consistent with both dimensional and categorical views of psychosis. However, no study to date has compared performance on these tasks across a mixed psychiatric inpatient population.</p><p id="p0045">This categorical-dimensional psychosis controversy is paralleled in the distinction between psychotic disorders and sub-threshold or non-clinical psychotic symptomatology conceptualised as schizotypy. Substantial evidence suggests that schizotypy and clinical schizophrenia have significant overlap in terms of genetic, biological and psychosocial factors (<xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr">Ripke et al., 2013</xref>). However, whether this is as an &#x0201c;endophenotype&#x0201d; in the general population for schizophrenia or if it is a distributed dimension throughout the entire population is contested (<xref rid="bb0055" ref-type="bibr">Grant et al., 2018</xref>). Moreover, there is limited conflicting data as to whether the impaired cognitive and perceptual domains observed in people with psychotic disorders also extend into schizotypy (<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Ettinger et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Sahakyan et al., 2019</xref>). The psychosis continuum theory would predict, similar to psychotic symptoms, cognitive and perceptual function would be diminished in participants with high schizotypy compared to participants with low schizotypy (<xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Xavier et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0050">The current study aimed to expand the current understanding by testing whether cognitive and perceptual dysfunction is specific to schizophrenia compared to other psychotic and non-psychotic disorders using the JOVI, RiSE and DPX, and if there is cognitive and perceptual function discontinuity between schizophrenia and schizotypy in these domains. Additionally, given the increasing use of online assessments, a sub aim was to assess the validity of the JOVI, RiSE and DPX in an online context.</p><p id="p0055">It was hypothesised that: (1) patients with schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders will show significantly worse performance on the three tasks than patients with non-psychotic disorders and healthy controls; and (2a) healthy controls with high schizotypy scores will show similar but milder patterns of cognitive impairment compared to patients with schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders, and (2b) that there will be a negative association between schizotypy and performance on the tasks.</p></sec><sec id="s0010"><label>2</label><title>Methods</title><sec id="s0015"><label>2.1</label><title>Participants</title><p id="p0060">The in-person sample was recruited from patients admitted to adult psychiatric inpatient units at two metropolitan hospitals (the Northern Hospital and the Monash Medical Centre) in Melbourne, Australia and opportunistically from staff, students and colleagues. Participants were patients who met DSM-IV (4th ed, Text Revision; DSM-IV-TR; <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr">American Psychiatric Association, 2000</xref>) criteria for schizophrenia and a range of other psychotic and non-psychotic disorders as assessed by an independent consultant psychiatrist, and healthy controls who did not meet criteria for any disorder.</p><p id="p0065">The online sample initially consisted of 153 participants. Three participants did not meet the age criterion, three used psychotropic medication and 36 had very poor task performance (i.e., accuracy below chance level). The final online sample consisted of 111 self-assessed healthy adults from Australia and the UK.</p><p id="p0070">Participation was voluntary, consent was informed (in-person study), participants could withdraw from the study at any time and participants were reimbursed for their time. Ethical approvals were obtained from the Melbourne Health and Monash University Human Research Ethics Committees.</p></sec><sec id="s0020"><label>2.2</label><title>Materials</title><sec id="s0025"><label>2.2.1</label><title>Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS)</title><p id="p0075">The PANSS measures positive symptoms, negative symptoms and general psychopathology through an assessment of behavioural manifestations via interview and reports from family members and hospital staff (<xref rid="bb0070" ref-type="bibr">Kay et al., 1987</xref>). It comprises 30 items and each item is scored from one to seven, ascending in severity.</p></sec><sec id="s0030"><label>2.2.2</label><title>Community Assessment of Psychic Experiences (CAPE)</title><p id="p0080">The CAPE is a 42 item self-report psychological inventory which measures the level of schizotypy in an individual (<xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr">Stefanis et al., 2002</xref>). The measure is not used to diagnose people but to assess the severity of schizotypy characteristics in the general population.</p></sec><sec id="s0035"><label>2.2.3</label><title>Jittered Orientation Visual Integration</title><p id="p0085">The JOVI task is composed of a background of Gabor elements, which correspond to the primary visual cortex receptive field organization, placed at various orientations (<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2012</xref>). Participants are required to identify fragmented egg shapes amongst this array and judge whether the shapes point towards the left or right by tapping the left and right arrow keys on their keyboard (<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2012</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="s0040"><label>2.2.4</label><title>Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task</title><p id="p0090">The RiSE is a psychometrically valid and reliable measure of relational and item-specific memory for healthy adults and individuals with schizophrenia (<xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Ragland et al., 2012</xref>). It involves four subtasks which measure item specific encoding, relational encoding, item specific retrieval and relational retrieval.</p></sec><sec id="s0045"><label>2.2.5</label><title>The Dot Pattern Expectancy Task</title><p id="p0095">The DPX task was used to measure goal maintenance. Participants were required to respond after a cue and probe stimuli and received auditory feedback after each stimulus. The DPX has shown to be a reliable measure of goal maintenance with a high internal consistency (<xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2010</xref>). To minimise response bias, response patterns were used to compute d'Context scores of overall sensitivity. Correct hits on the target &#x0201c;AX&#x0201d; trials were calculated as: (Correct hits&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;0.05)&#x000a0;/&#x000a0;(Total target trials&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;1); and the false alarms on the rule-based &#x0201c;BX&#x0201d; trials as (False alarms&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;0.05)&#x000a0;/&#x000a0;(Total rule-based trials&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;1). d'Context scores were then computed using a formula recommended by <xref rid="bb0085" ref-type="bibr">Macmillan and Creelman (1996)</xref>: d'Context&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;z(Hit rate)&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;z(False alarms).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0050"><label>2.3</label><title>Procedure</title><sec id="s0055"><label>2.3.1</label><title>In-person study</title><p id="p0100">All in-person participants first completed a demographics questionnaire that screened for eligibility, and assessed age, gender, education level, diagnosis, illness duration, substance use and psychiatric history. Participants then commenced the tasks: JOVI, RiSE and DPX, where instructions were read aloud to every participant and participants completed practice trials for that task. Practice trials were administered as per the CNTRACS protocols (<xref rid="bb0145" ref-type="bibr">Silverstein et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr">Ragland et al., 2012</xref>; <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Jones et al., 2010</xref>) and when criteria were met participants proceeded to the task questions. Note that in-person participation varied between tasks (specific participant numbers and demographic details for each task are in <xref rid="t0030" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>). The in-person participants also completed the NART (National Adult Reading Test; <xref rid="bb0100" ref-type="bibr">Nelson and Wilson, 1991</xref>) and patients were administered the PANSS. Participants were permitted to take a short break between task blocks if required. The overall duration of the in-person study was approximately 4&#x000a0;h.</p></sec><sec id="s0060"><label>2.3.2</label><title>Online schizotypy study</title><p id="p0105">The study was advertised online via the Amazon MTurk recruitment website. Participants were asked to read the eligibility criteria and the study information sheet before providing their consent. Participant task submissions were de-identified through MTurk's process of assigning anonymous Worker Number IDs. Participants first completed a demographics form providing their computer screen dimensions and resolution, age, country of birth, education level, employment status, gender, medical conditions and medications and primary language. Participants were then redirected to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://Pavlovia.org" id="ir0005">Pavlovia.org</ext-link>, where they commenced the three cognitive tasks. The order of the JOVI, RiSE and DPX tasks varied between participants to account for differences in performance due to task order. Practice trials were embedded at the beginning of each of the tasks. After this, participants completed the CAPE. The duration of the study was approximately 1&#x000a0;h, however participants had 3&#x000a0;h available to complete the tasks.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0065"><label>2.4</label><title>Statistical analyses</title><p id="p0110">Spearman's correlational analyses were performed to assess any confounding effects of age, on d'Context, RiSE, JOVI, CAPE-42, and PANSS scores. Age was identified as a confounding variable in JOVI and RiSE in-person and online samples. No moderating variables were found in the DPX in-person sample, but age and education level were identified in the DPX online sample.</p><p id="p0115">To assess the size and direction of the linear association between performance on the cognitive and perceptual tasks and scores on the PANSS and its component subscales for the patient group, a Spearman's rank correlation coefficient (<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>) was calculated with a Bonferroni adjusted &#x003b1; level of 0.016 (0.05/3) per test. To assess the size and direction of the linear association between performance on the cognitive tasks and scores on the CAPE and its component subscales for the online healthy control group, a Spearman's rank correlation coefficient (<italic>r</italic><sub><italic>s</italic></sub>) was calculated with a Bonferroni adjusted &#x003b1; level of 0.016 (0.05/3) per test. Unless otherwise stated, an alpha level (&#x003b1;) of 0.05 was used in the analyses.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0070"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><sec id="s0075"><label>3.1</label><title>Demographic and clinical data</title><p id="p0120">Demographic information including sample size, sex, age and location for all participant groups and in each of the tasks is shown in <xref rid="t0005" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0005"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Demographic data for both online and in-person participant groups.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0015">Table 1</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2"/><th colspan="5">DPX<hr/></th><th colspan="5">RiSE<hr/></th><th colspan="5">JOVI<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Online HC</th><th>In-person HC</th><th>SZ</th><th>PS</th><th>Non-PS</th><th>Online HC</th><th>In-person HC</th><th>SZ</th><th>PS</th><th>Non-PS</th><th>Online HC</th><th>In-person HC</th><th>SZ</th><th>PS</th><th>Non-PS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>N</td><td>105</td><td>20</td><td>16</td><td>12</td><td>8</td><td>111</td><td>20</td><td>17</td><td>9</td><td>9</td><td>102</td><td>20</td><td>13</td><td>11</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>Sex</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Female</td><td>40</td><td>10</td><td>6</td><td>4</td><td>4</td><td>41</td><td>10</td><td>7</td><td>5</td><td>6</td><td>39</td><td>10</td><td>4</td><td>8</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Male</td><td>64</td><td>10</td><td>10</td><td>8</td><td>4</td><td>69</td><td>10</td><td>10</td><td>4</td><td>3</td><td>63</td><td>10</td><td>9</td><td>3</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>M<sub>age</sub> (SD)</td><td>30.60 (8.81)</td><td>28.00 (12.1)</td><td>37.10 (8.1)</td><td>33.80 (8.5)</td><td>31.00 (7.5)</td><td>30.20 (8.78)</td><td>25.70 (8.34)</td><td>38.35 (5.93)</td><td>38.33 (10.05)</td><td>45.33 (12.69)</td><td>31.01 (8.93)</td><td>28.00 (12.09)</td><td>38.60 (9.30)</td><td>34.50 (8.49)</td><td>31.00 (7.54)</td></tr><tr><td>Location</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;UK</td><td>49</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>51</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>47</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Australia</td><td>56</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>60</td><td/><td/><td/><td/><td>55</td><td/><td/><td/><td/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>DPX&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Dot Expectancy Task, RiSE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task, JOVI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Jittered Orientation Visual Integration, HC&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;healthy control, SZ&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;schizophrenia, PS&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;other psychoses, Non-PS&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;non-psychosis.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0080"><label>3.2</label><title>Symptom and schizotypy ratings</title><p id="p0125">The descriptive statistics for the PANSS scores associated with the psychiatric inpatient sample are provided in <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>. As the online samples were not fully overlapping, descriptive statistics for the CAPE measures relating to the participants included in the JOVI, RiSE and DPX task analyses are provided in <xref rid="t0015" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0010"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics (mean (standard deviation)) for Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) total and subscale scores for all participants in the in-person psychiatric inpatient study.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0020">Table 2</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>PANSS total</th><th>PANSS positive</th><th>PANSS negative</th><th>PANSS disorganised</th><th>PANSS general psychopathology</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>JOVI dataset</td><td>73.31 (13.92)</td><td>18.09 (5.89)</td><td>16.88 (6.83)</td><td>20.56 (7.55)</td><td>38.34 (7.06)</td></tr><tr><td>RiSE dataset</td><td>52.43 (9.44)</td><td>15.11 (6.30)</td><td>10.77 (3.62)</td><td>15.63 (4.89)</td><td>26.54 (4.87)</td></tr><tr><td>DPX dataset</td><td>74.17 (14.55)</td><td>18.53 (5.97)</td><td>16.92 (6.91)</td><td>21.33 (7.70)</td><td>38.72 (7.47)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>JOVI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Jittered Orientation Visual Integration, RiSE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task, DPX&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Dot Expectancy Task.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t0015"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Descriptive statistics (mean (standard deviation)) for Community Assessment of Psychic Experiences (CAPE) total and subscale scores for all participants in the online schizotypy study.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0025">Table 3</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>CAPE total</th><th>CAPE positive</th><th>CAPE negative</th><th>CAPE depressive</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>JOVI dataset</td><td>70.96 (15.50)</td><td>1.46 (0.34)</td><td>1.89 (0.53)</td><td>1.90 (0.52)</td></tr><tr><td>RiSE dataset</td><td>70.60 (15.22)</td><td>1.46 (0.34)</td><td>1.88 (0.52)</td><td>1.88 (0.51)</td></tr><tr><td>DPX dataset</td><td>71.09 (15.40)</td><td>1.47 (0.34)</td><td>1.90 (0.52)</td><td>1.90 (0.52)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>JOVI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Jittered Orientation Visual Integration, RiSE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task, DPX&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Dot Expectancy Task.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p></sec><sec id="s0085"><label>3.3</label><title>Between group differences in task performance</title><sec id="s0090"><label>3.3.1</label><title>JOVI</title><p id="p0130">An ANCOVA, covarying for age, between the online healthy control, in-person healthy control, non-psychosis, other psychoses, and schizophrenia patient groups revealed statistically significant differences in JOVI scores (F(4, 98)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.762, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup><sub>g</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.163). As shown in <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>A, controlling for age, Tukey post hoc analyses revealed the in-person healthy controls (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.77, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.06) performed significantly better on the JOVI than the non-psychosis (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.68, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.07), the other psychoses (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.67, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.08) and the schizophrenia groups (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.67, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.09). There were no significant differences between the online healthy controls (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.73, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.07) and the in-person healthy controls.<fig id="f0005"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Group comparisons of performance on the A. Jittered Orientation Visual Integration (JOVI); B. Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task (RiSE); and C. Dot Expectancy Task expressed as d'Context (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>). Lines over plots represent groups which were significantly different. *p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.05; **p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.01; HC&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;healthy control.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0005">Fig. 1</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr1"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="s0095"><label>3.3.2</label><title>RiSE</title><p id="p0135">An ANCOVA, covarying for age, revealed a significant main effect between groups (F(4,160)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;17.93, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.001, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup><sub>g</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.310) on RiSE task performance (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>B). Tukey post hoc analyses revealed RiSE scores were significantly higher for online (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;11.20, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.32) and in-person (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.25, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.20) healthy control groups compared to the schizophrenia group (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.82, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.92). There were also significant differences between the online healthy control group and the other psychoses (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.89, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.73) and the non-psychosis (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5.89, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.73) groups. No other significant differences were found.</p></sec><sec id="s0100"><label>3.3.3</label><title>DPX</title><p id="p0140">A Kruskal-Wallis test demonstrated statistically significant differences in performance on the DPX task between groups (Chi square&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;37.07, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.001, df&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5, &#x003b7;<sup>2</sup><sub>H</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.305) (<xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>C). Multiple comparison post-hoc analyses with Dunn's test revealed that schizophrenia patients had significantly lower d'Context scores (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.11, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.57) than online (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.70, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.23) and in-person (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.82, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.15) healthy controls. There were no significant differences in performance on the task between patients with schizophrenia, non-psychosis (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.92, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05) and other psychoses groups (<italic>M</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.72, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.22).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0105"><label>3.4</label><title>Association between symptom profiles and schizotypy scores and task performance</title><sec id="s0110"><label>3.4.1</label><title>In-person study</title><p id="p0145">For both, RiSE overall accuracy and DPX ranked d'Context scores, there were significant negative correlations with PANSS total scores, and the positive and disorganised subscales (<xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>).<table-wrap position="float" id="t0020"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Spearman's correlations between overall task accuracy for the Jittered Orientation Visual Integration (JOVI) (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;32), Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task (RiSE) (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;35) and Dot Expectancy Task (n&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;36) and Positive and Negative Syndrome Scale (PANSS) total and sub-scale scores for all participants in the in-person psychiatric inpatient study.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0030">Table 4</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Task</th><th>PANSS total</th><th>PANSS positive</th><th>PANSS negative</th><th>PANSS disorganised</th><th>PANSS general</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>JOVI</td><td>0.048 (0.799)</td><td>&#x02212;0.176 (0.336)</td><td>0.089 (0.630)</td><td>&#x02212;0.226 (0.214)</td><td>0.108 (0.556)</td></tr><tr><td>RiSE</td><td>&#x02212;0.419 (0.012)<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#x0204e;</xref></td><td>&#x02212;0.473 (0.004)<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#x0204e;</xref></td><td>&#x02212;0.230 (0.184)</td><td>&#x02212;0.456 (0.006)<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#x0204e;</xref></td><td>&#x02212;0.030 (0.866)</td></tr><tr><td>DPX</td><td>&#x02212;0.41 (0.012)<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#x0204e;</xref></td><td>&#x02212;0.63 (&#x0003c;0.001)<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#x0204e;</xref></td><td>&#x02212;0.05 (0.780)</td><td>&#x02212;0.60 (&#x0003c;0.001)<xref rid="tf0005" ref-type="table-fn">&#x0204e;</xref></td><td>&#x02212;0.15 (0.387)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label><p id="np0005">p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.016.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="s0115"><label>3.4.1.1</label><title>Psychotropic medication</title><p id="p0150">Antipsychotic drug doses (expressed as chlorpromazine equivalents) and benzodiazepine drug doses (expressed as diazepam equivalents) (<xref rid="t0030" ref-type="table">Table 6</xref>) showed no significant differences between patient groups for those completing the RiSE and DPX tasks. For those completing the JOVI task, Kruskal-Wallis analysis demonstrated statistically significant differences in antipsychotic doses between clinical groups (F(2,32)&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.07, p&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;.018) with a pairwise Wilcoxon analysis showing significantly higher doses in the Other Psychoses (M<sub>D</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;254.56, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.042) and the Schizophrenia (M<sub>D</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;321.07, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.036) groups compared to the Non-Psychosis group. However, there were no differences in benzodiazepine doses for this group. Antipsychotic drug dose did not significantly correlate with task performance on the JOVI (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.099, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.589), RiSE (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.217, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.345) or DPX (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.941, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.354); nor did benzodiazepine drug dose and task performance on the JOVI (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.24, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.184), RiSE (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.087, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.777) or DPX (r&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.695, p&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.492).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s0120"><label>3.4.2</label><title>Online study</title><p id="p0155">As shown in <xref rid="t0025" ref-type="table">Table 5</xref>, there were no statistically significant associations between performance on the cognitive tasks and scores on the CAPE and its component subscales.<table-wrap position="float" id="t0025"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Spearman's correlations between overall task accuracy for the Jittered Orientation Visual Integration (JOVI), Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task (RiSE) and Dot Expectancy Task and Community Assessment of Psychic Experiences (CAPE) total and subscale scores for all participants in the online schizotypy study.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0035">Table 5</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>CAPE total</th><th>CAPE positive</th><th>CAPE negative</th><th>CAPE depressive</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>JOVI dataset</td><td>0.067 (0.506)</td><td>0.038 (0.711)</td><td>0.056 (0.575)</td><td>0.053 (0.598)</td></tr><tr><td>RiSE dataset</td><td>&#x02212;0.146 (0.131)</td><td>&#x02212;0.192 (0.045)</td><td>&#x02212;0.100 (0.301)</td><td>&#x02212;0.063 (0.514)</td></tr><tr><td>DPX dataset</td><td>&#x02212;0.12 (0.223)</td><td>&#x02212;0.01 (0.912)</td><td>&#x02212;0.12 (0.218)</td><td>&#x02212;0.20 (0.039)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values in parentheses are p-values.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="t0030"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Diagnostic and treatment data for the in-person psychiatric participant groups.</p></caption><alt-text id="al0040">Table 6</alt-text><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th/><th>RiSE patient group</th><th>DPX patient group</th><th>JOVI patient group</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Schizophrenia group</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;First episode psychosis</td><td>0</td><td>0</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Schizoaffective disorder</td><td>10</td><td>8</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Schizophrenia</td><td>7</td><td>8</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>Other Psychoses group</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Post-partum psychosis</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Bipolar affective disorder</td><td>1</td><td>9</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Depression with psychotic features</td><td>0</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Complex PTSD</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Non-Psychosis group</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Depression</td><td>4</td><td>5</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Depression with comorbid anxiety</td><td>1</td><td>1</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Substance abuse</td><td>1</td><td>2</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Borderline personality disorder</td><td>1</td><td>0</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>Medication</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Antipsychotics</td><td>29</td><td>30</td><td>28</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Benzodiazepines</td><td>17</td><td>10</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4">&#x02028;&#x02028;</td></tr></tbody></table><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Chlorpromazine equivalent (mg)</th><th>RiSE patient group<hr/></th><th>DPX patient group<hr/></th><th>JOVI patient group<hr/></th></tr><tr><th>Mean (SD<xref rid="tf0010" ref-type="table-fn">a</xref>)</th><th>Mean (SD)</th><th>Mean (SD)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Antipsychotics daily dose</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Schizophrenia group</td><td>621.82 (529.16)</td><td>487.86 (390.88)</td><td>437.78 (383.59)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Other Psychoses group</td><td>298.00 (118.83)</td><td>369.00 (224.04)</td><td>371.27 (234.77)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Non-Psychosis group</td><td>154.00 (169.72)</td><td>233.25 (151.71)</td><td>116.71 (159.44)</td></tr><tr><td>Benzodiazepine daily dose (mg)</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Schizophrenia group</td><td>23.00 (32.52)</td><td>12.50 (5.00)</td><td>10.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Other Psychoses group</td><td>17.50 (13.92)</td><td>8.33 (2.89)</td><td>10.00 (0.00)</td></tr><tr><td>&#x000a0;Non-Psychosis group</td><td>21.00 (19.17)</td><td>13.33 (5.77)</td><td>13.33 (5.77)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="sp0065"><p>Numbers reported are <italic>n</italic> unless otherwise stated.</p></fn><fn id="sp0070"><p>JOVI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Jittered Orientation Visual Integration, RiSE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task, DPX&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Dot Expectancy Task; PTSD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;post-traumatic stress disorder.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf0010"><label>a</label><p id="np0010">SD&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p><sec id="s0125"><label>3.4.2.1</label><title>Online schizotypy sample versus in-person healthy controls cognitive function</title><p id="p0160">As shown in <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig">Fig. 2</xref>, there were no significant differences in task performance between the online low and high schizotypy groups and in-person healthy controls. Low and high schizotypy groups were formed by splitting the online group into quartiles based on total CAPE score and selecting the lowest and highest quartiles.<fig id="f0010"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Group comparisons between the online low and high schizotypy and in-person healthy control (HC; <italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;20) groups of performance on the A. Jittered Orientation Visual Integration (JOVI; <italic>n</italic><sub>low</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;27, <italic>n</italic><sub>high</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;25); B. Computerised item Specific and Relational Memory Cognitive Task (RiSE; <italic>n</italic><sub>low</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;29, <italic>n</italic><sub>high</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;28); and C. Dot Expectancy Task expressed as d'Context (see <xref rid="s0010" ref-type="sec">Methods</xref>; <italic>n</italic><sub>low</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;27, <italic>n</italic><sub>high</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;28).</p></caption><alt-text id="al0010">Fig. 2</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="gr2"/></fig></p></sec></sec></sec></sec><sec id="s0130"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><p id="p0165">Visual integration, relational memory and goal maintenance are processes that are commonly impaired in individuals with schizophrenia, though substantially less is known about how these cognitive impairments relate to other psychotic disorders and schizotypy.</p><p id="p0170">This study first explored if impairments in these tasks were specific to schizophrenia or if they generalised to other psychotic and non-psychotic disorders. While clear differences were seen between individuals with a diagnosis of schizophrenia and healthy controls, no differences were found between patients with schizophrenia or other psychoses. These findings contrast with claims regarding the diagnostic specificity of impaired performance on the JOVI, RiSE and DPX tasks but are consistent with other work similarly demonstrating that cognitive and perceptual impairments observed in schizophrenia extend to other psychotic disorders (<xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr">Barch et al., 2003</xref>; <xref rid="bb0105" ref-type="bibr">Owoso et al., 2013</xref>; <xref rid="bb0155" ref-type="bibr">Smucny et al., 2020</xref>). These findings align with a dimensional perspective of cognitive and perceptual dysfunction in psychotic disorders differentiating them from non-psychotic disorders and potential confounds such as medication. Moreover, the diagnostic heterogeneity within the other psychoses group and the correlational relationships with psychotic symptoms is suggestive of some possible common mechanisms underlying both these symptoms and cognitive and perceptual domains independent of diagnosis.</p><p id="p0175">The current study further aimed to investigate whether there is continuity in function between schizotypy in healthy controls and patients diagnosed with schizophrenia, across the domains of goal maintenance, relational memory, and contour integration. The hypothesis that healthy controls with high schizotypy scores will show similar but milder patterns of cognitive impairment compared to patients with schizophrenia was not supported. Results for the RiSE and DPX tasks showed no significant difference between the high and low schizotypy groups and both were superior to the schizophrenia group. In the case of the JOVI measure of contour integration, the difference between the performance of the online healthy control group was not significantly different from the schizophrenia group however there was again no significant difference between high and low schizotypy group. These findings demonstrate some discontinuity in cognitive and perceptual performance between schizophrenia and people with high schizotypy. This could be consistent with the transition to schizophrenia requiring additional factors to those for psychosis-like symptoms including different neural substrates for sub-threshold symptoms and cognitive and perceptual functioning. These data could also be consistent with a sharp demarcation between schizophrenia and schizotypy in the general population. Until now there have been no studies comparing the performance of healthy controls with high schizotypy against schizophrenia patients on the JOVI, RiSE and DPX. Therefore, this study is the first to demonstrate that cognitive and perceptual performance in these three domains is not dimensional along a sub-threshold non-clinical to clinical psychosis continuum.</p><p id="p0180">Moreover, we found no statistically significant correlation between task performance and schizotypy scores and no difference in task performance when the healthy control group was dichotomised into high versus low schizotypy. This argues against cognitive and perceptual impairments in psychosis sharing a transitional profile into a non-clinical psychosis-like dimension. The current findings are consistent with a recent study (<xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Sahakyan et al., 2019</xref>), which found no correlation between relational memory and overall schizotypy levels. However, it contrasts with earlier work showing a gradation of increasing cognitive task impairments from low to high schizotypy that was accompanied by brain activity changes consistent with those seen in individuals with schizophrenia (<xref rid="bb0040" ref-type="bibr">Ettinger et al., 2015</xref>; <xref rid="bb0185" ref-type="bibr">Xavier et al., 2015</xref>).</p><p id="p0185">The study also sought to determine whether the online and in-person versions of the JOVI, RiSE and DPX tasks produced similar performance levels across two different non-clinical samples. Our results showed no statistically significant differences between the online and the in-person healthy control group task scores. This demonstrates for the first time the validity of using the JOVI, RiSE and DPX tasks in an online setting, at least in the general population.</p><p id="p0190">While the online format did not allow for a fully controlled study environment, which may have influenced the outcome, it had other advantages over in-person assessment. Implementing computerized cognitive tasks and collecting data in a novel online format allowed efficient sample recruitment. Additionally, despite the participants in patient groups receiving different medication types and doses, there were no statistically significant differences in task performance and there were no significant correlations between task performance and drug dose. Thus, it is unlikely that medication significantly influenced the results of the current study. As is reflected in the PANSS scores presented in <xref rid="t0020" ref-type="table">Table 4</xref>, illness severity in the in-patient participant groups is mild-moderate which was considered sufficiently stable to manage participation in the tasks, and unlikely to have influenced task performance. Finally, it is possible that the lack of significant group differences between psychiatric groups on the CNTRACS measures may be due to low statistical power as a result of small sample sizes for the in-person patient groups.</p><p id="p0195">The current study's findings support the notion that cognitive and perceptual impairments in schizophrenia extend to other psychotic disorders but are discontinuous with schizotypy. Our findings suggest that cognitive deficits that are present in schizophrenia are not present in individuals with high schizotypy and it therefore does not support schizotypy as a useful construct to study cognitive and perceptual deficits in schizophrenia. This study provides insights into similarities between schizophrenia and other psychotic disorders with regards to the potential neural substrates underpinning these cognitive and perceptual functions.</p></sec><sec id="s0135"><title>Ethical approval</title><p id="p0200">Ethical approval for the study was given by the Melbourne Health (for the Northern Hospital site and in-person healthy control arms) and Monash University (for the Monash Medical Centre site and online arms) Human Research Ethics Committees and all participants gave informed consent.</p></sec><sec id="s0140"><title>Funding sources</title><p id="p0205">Funding was provided by <funding-source id="gts0005">internal departmental research funds</funding-source>.</p></sec><sec id="s0145"><title>CRediT authorship contribution statement</title><p id="p0210">
<list list-type="simple" id="l0010"><list-item id="li0020"><p id="p0215">NF, MG and DR: investigation, formal analysis, writing &#x02013; original draft</p></list-item><list-item id="li0025"><p id="p0220">HD: methodology, software, formal analysis, project administration, supervision, resources, writing &#x02013; review and editing</p></list-item><list-item id="li0030"><p id="p0225">CR, TM and MM: investigation, formal analysis</p></list-item><list-item id="li0035"><p id="p0230">RH: supervision, resources, writing &#x02013; review and editing</p></list-item><list-item id="li0040"><p id="p0235">OC: conceptualisation, methodology, supervision, resources, funding acquisition, writing &#x02013; review and editing</p></list-item><list-item id="li0045"><p id="p0240">SS: conceptualisation, supervision, resources, funding acquisition, writing &#x02013; review and editing.</p></list-item></list>
</p></sec><sec sec-type="COI-statement"><title>Declaration of competing interest</title><p id="p0270">Authors report no potential conflicts of interest relevant to the current paper.</p></sec></body><back><ref-list id="bi0005"><title>References</title><ref id="bb0005"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202207300429401618"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>American Psychiatric Association</collab></person-group><part-title>Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders</part-title><edition>4th ed.</edition><year>2000</year><comment>Text Revision</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0010"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425461978"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Braver</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Context-processing deficits in schizophrenia: Diagnostic specificity, 4-week course, and relationships to clinical symptoms</article-title><source>J. Abnorm. Psychol.</source><volume>112</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2003</year><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>143</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-843X.112.1.132</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12653421</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0015"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300436203304"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Engle</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonides</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Nee</surname><given-names>D.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Redick</surname><given-names>T.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sponheim</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CNTRICS final task selection: working memory</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>35</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>136</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18990711</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0020"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300436193934"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive neuroscience-based approaches to measuring and improving treatment effects on cognition in schizophrenia: the CNTRICS initiative</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>33</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2007</year><fpage>1131</fpage><lpage>1137</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1093/schbul/sbm081" id="ir0010">https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1093/schbul/sbm081</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17630405</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0030"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425563638"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Servan-Schreiber</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Context-processing deficits in schizophrenia: converging evidence from three theoretically motivated cognitive tasks</article-title><source>J. Abnorm. Psychol.</source><volume>108</volume><issue>1</issue><year>1999</year><fpage>120</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0021-843X.108.1.120</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10066998</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0035"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300429161488"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>East-Richard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mercier</surname><given-names>R.-A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nadeau</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cellard</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transdiagnostic neurocognitive deficits in psychiatry: a review of meta-analyses</article-title><source>Can. Psychol.</source><volume>61</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>214</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/cap0000196</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0040"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300436132884"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ettinger</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohr</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gooding</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rapp</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haenschel</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Park</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognition and brain function in schizotypy: a selective review</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>41</volume><issue>Suppl. 2</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>S417</fpage><lpage>S426</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbu190</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25810056</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0045"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300426092198"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive neuroscience test reliability and clinical applications for schizophrenia</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>103</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbr173</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22199091</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0050"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300436121724"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luck</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Clinical, functional, and intertask correlations of measures developed by the cognitive neuroscience test reliability and clinical applications for schizophrenia consortium</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>144</fpage><lpage>152</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1093/schbul/sbr142" id="ir0015">https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1093/schbul/sbr142</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22101961</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0055"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300426114138"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>M.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mason</surname><given-names>O.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Models of schizotypy: the importance of conceptual clarity</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>44</volume><issue>suppl_2</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>S556</fpage><lpage>S563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sby012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29474661</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0060"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435574004"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>New possibilities in cognition enhancement for schizophrenia</article-title><source>Am. J. Psychiatry</source><volume>166</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>749</fpage><lpage>752</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2009.09050610</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19570935</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0065"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435561874"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sponheim</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>The dot pattern expectancy task: reliability and replication of deficits in schizophrenia</article-title><source>Psychol. Assess.</source><volume>22</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>141</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1037/a0017828" id="ir0020">https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1037/a0017828</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20230159</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0070"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435502414"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>S.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fiszbein</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Opler</surname><given-names>L.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The positive and negative syndrome scale (PANSS) for schizophrenia</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>13</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1987</year><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>276</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1093/schbul/13.2.261" id="ir0025">https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.1093/schbul/13.2.261</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3616518</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0075"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425536739"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Erlikhman</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kastner</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterno</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple forms of contour grouping deficits in schizophrenia: what is the role of spatial frequency</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>65</volume><year>2014</year><fpage>221</fpage><lpage>233</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2014.10.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25446968</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0080"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435451114"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lopez-Garcia</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesh</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salo</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The neural circuitry supporting goal maintenance during cognitive control: a comparison of expectancy AX-CPT and dot probe expectancy paradigms</article-title><source>Cogn. Affect. Behav. Neurosci.</source><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>175</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.3758/s13415-015-0384-1" id="ir0030">https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.3758/s13415-015-0384-1</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26494483</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0085"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435346014"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Macmillan</surname><given-names>N.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Creelman</surname><given-names>C.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Triangles in ROC space: history and theory of &#x0201c;nonparametric&#x0201d; measures of sensitivity and response bias</article-title><source>Psychon. Bull. Rev.</source><volume>3</volume><issue>2</issue><year>1996</year><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.3758/BF03212415" id="ir0035">https://doi-org.ezproxy.lib.monash.edu.au/10.3758/BF03212415</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24213864</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0090"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435286024"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McCleery</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuechterlein</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive impairment in psychotic illness: prevalence, profile of impairment, developmental course, and treatment considerations</article-title><source>Dialogues Clin. Neurosci.</source><volume>21</volume><issue>3</issue><year>2019</year><fpage>239</fpage><lpage>248</lpage><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://10.31887/DCNS.2019.21.3/amccleery" id="ir0040">https://10.31887/DCNS.2019.21.3/amccleery</ext-link><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31749648</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0095"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425527968"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mukherjee</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabharwal</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kotov</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Szekely</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parsey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mohanty</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Disconnection between amygdala and medial prefrontal cortex in psychotic disorders</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>42</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1056</fpage><lpage>1067</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbw012</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26908926</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0100"><element-citation publication-type="book" id="rf202207300435226135"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nelson</surname><given-names>H.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><part-title>National Adult Reading Test (NART)</part-title><year>1991</year><publisher-name>NFER-Nelson</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Windsor, UK</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0105"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435031365"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Owoso</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognition in schizophrenia and schizo-affective disorder: impairments that are more similar than different</article-title><source>Psychol. Med.</source><volume>43</volume><issue>12</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>2535</fpage><lpage>2545</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/s0033291713000536</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23522057</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0110"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300435021895"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poppe</surname><given-names>A.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced frontoparietal activity in schizophrenia is linked to a specific deficit in goal maintenance: a multisite functional imaging study</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>42</volume><issue>5</issue><year>2016</year><fpage>1149</fpage><lpage>1157</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbw036</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27060129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0115"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300434183915"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laird</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumenfeld</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzales</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glahn</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prefrontal activation deficits during episodic memory in schizophrenia</article-title><source>Am. J. Psychiatry</source><volume>166</volume><issue>8</issue><year>2009</year><fpage>863</fpage><lpage>874</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1176/appi.ajp.2009.08091307</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19411370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0120"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300434175625"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haley</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names><suffix>3rd</suffix></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonelinas</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Relational and item-specific encoding (RISE): task development and psychometric characteristics</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>114</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbr146</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22124089</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0125"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300434166795"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranganath</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Layher</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesh</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Niendam</surname><given-names>T.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yonelinas</surname><given-names>A.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Functional and neuroanatomic specificity of episodic memory dysfunction in schizophrenia: a functional magnetic resonance imaging study of the relational and item-specific encoding task</article-title><source>JAMA Psychiatry</source><volume>72</volume><issue>9</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>909</fpage><lpage>916</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jamapsychiatry.2015.0276</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26200928</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0130"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300434118835"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ripke</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Dushlaine</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chambert</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moran</surname><given-names>J.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahler</surname><given-names>A.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Akterin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bergen</surname><given-names>S.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>A.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crowley</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fromer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnusson</surname><given-names>P.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stahl</surname><given-names>E.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wray</surname><given-names>N.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettella</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sullivan</surname><given-names>P.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genome-wide association analysis identifies 13 new risk loci for schizophrenia</article-title><source>Nat. Genet.</source><volume>45</volume><issue>10</issue><year>2013</year><fpage>1150</fpage><lpage>1159</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng.2742</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23974872</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0135"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425526009"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sahakyan</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kwapil</surname><given-names>T.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lo</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Examination of relational memory in multidimensional schizotypy</article-title><source>Schizophr. Res.</source><volume>211</volume><year>2019</year><fpage>36</fpage><lpage>43</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.schres.2019.07.031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">31383512</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0140"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300434112105"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sheffield</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Karcher</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive deficits in psychotic disorders: a lifespan perspective</article-title><source>Neuropsychol. Rev.</source><volume>28</volume><issue>4</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>533</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11065-018-9388-2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30343458</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0145"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425520838"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kovacs</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Optimization and validation of a visual integration test for schizophrenia research</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>38</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2012</year><fpage>125</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbr141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22021658</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0150"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300434105615"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>B.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.</given-names><suffix>III</suffix></name><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cortical contributions to impaired contour integration in schizophrenia</article-title><source>Neuropsychologia</source><volume>75</volume><year>2015</year><fpage>469</fpage><lpage>480</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2015.07.003</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26160288</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0155"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300434096035"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smucny</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iosif</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eaton</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lesh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragland</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Barch</surname><given-names>D.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gold</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>M.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>A.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Latent profiles of cognitive control, episodic memory, and visual perception across psychiatric disorders reveal a dimensional structure</article-title><source>Schizophr. Bull.</source><volume>46</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2020</year><fpage>154</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/schbul/sbz025</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30953588</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0160"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425510568"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stefanis</surname><given-names>N.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanssen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smirnis</surname><given-names>N.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avramopoulos</surname><given-names>D.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Evdokimidis</surname><given-names>I.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanis</surname><given-names>C.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verdoux</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Os</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence that three dimensions of psychosis have a distribution in the general population</article-title><source>Psychol. Med.</source><volume>32</volume><issue>2</issue><year>2002</year><fpage>347</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291701005141</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11866327</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0165"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425499729"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tripathi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kar</surname><given-names>S.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shukla</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cognitive deficits in schizophrenia: understanding the biological correlates and remediation strategies</article-title><source>Clin. Psychopharmacol. Neurosci.</source><volume>16</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2018</year><fpage>7</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.9758/cpn.2018.16.1.7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29397662</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0175"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300429594118"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wells</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Swaminathan</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundram</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinberg</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruggemann</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacomb</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cropley</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenroot</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pereira</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zalesky</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bousman</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantelis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weickert</surname><given-names>C.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weickert</surname><given-names>T.W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The impact of premorbid and current intellect in schizophrenia: Cognitive, symptom, and functional outcomes</article-title><source>NPJ Schizophr.</source><volume>1</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>8</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/npjschz.2015.43</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0180"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300425482689"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>L.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Must</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Avery</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woolard</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>N.D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>N.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckers</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Eye-movement behavior reveals relational memory impairment in schizophrenia</article-title><source>Biol. Psychiatry</source><volume>68</volume><issue>7</issue><year>2010</year><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>624</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biopsych.2010.05.035</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20655509</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bb0185"><element-citation publication-type="journal" id="rf202207300429412608"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Best</surname><given-names>M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schorr</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowie</surname><given-names>C.R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Neurocognition, functional competence and self-reported functional impairment in psychometrically defined schizotypy</article-title><source>Cogn. Neuropsychiatry</source><volume>20</volume><issue>1</issue><year>2015</year><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13546805.2014.969419</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25341444</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list><ack id="ac0005"><title>Acknowledgements</title><p id="p0275">We thank Ms Sumathy Sathiyamoorthy at the Northern Hospital and all staff of the adult psychiatric inpatients units at both the Northern Hospital and Monash Medical Centre for assistance with recruitment of participants.</p></ack></back></article>