<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="book-review"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pbrcpsych</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Royal College of Psychiatrists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5451659</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/pb.bp.116.054189</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Columns</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Reviews</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>MCQs in Psychiatry for Medical Students</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Dash</surname><given-names>Suzanne</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p><bold>Suzanne Dash</bold>, graduate-entry medical student, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK; email: <email>suzanne.dash@medschool.ox.ac.uk</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>41</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage seq="b">183</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><product><source><bold>MCQs in Psychiatry for Medical Students</bold></source><comment> By </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><name><surname>Lally</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><comment> and </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><name><surname>Tully</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><comment>. </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><publisher-name>RCPsych Publications</publisher-name><comment>, </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><year>2016</year><comment>, </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><comment>&#x000a3;18.00</comment><x>. </x><comment> (</comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><comment>&#x000a3;16.20</comment><x>. </x><comment> for College members), pb, </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><comment>224 pp.</comment><comment> ISBN: </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><isbn>9781909726482</isbn><x>. </x></product><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2017 The Author</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2017</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article published by the Royal College of Psychiatrists and distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="183.pdf"/></article-meta></front><body><p id="P1">Love them or loathe them, most medical student written examinations now take the form of multiple choice questions (MCQs). Some medical educators dislike this assessment style, suggesting it encourages students to learn isolated facts in a superficial way. Yet, undeniably, MCQs provide an objective, time-efficient manner of evaluation.</p><p id="P2"><italic>MCQs in Psychiatry for Medical Students</italic> is a valuable resource for medical students undertaking their psychiatry rotations. It includes MCQs and extended matching items grouped into chapters concerned either with a type of disorder &#x02013; for example, psychotic disorders and alcohol and substance misuse disorders &#x02013; or another important aspect of psychiatry, such as physical health, pharmacological treatments, psychology and psychotherapy.</p><p id="P3">Each MCQ is accompanied by a paragraph or two explaining the correct answer. More information is provided than is strictly necessary to understand the answer, but this is illuminating rather than turgid. The 400-plus contemporary references encourage the reader to consider issues in more depth than the superficial learning style many associate with MCQs, making the scope of this book potentially greater than is obvious from its title. In contrast, the three extended matching item questions in each chapter are not followed by explanations, making them far less informative.</p><p id="P4">Writing good MCQ distractor items is a challenge, and in a few places &#x02013; especially questions on risk factors and protective factors &#x02013; it is possible to guess the answer by eliminating answers simply based on whether they describe something positive or negative.</p><p id="P5">This is a must-have title for all medical students; it will pique the interest of many students and may even assist in recruiting future psychiatrists to the profession.</p></body></article>