<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pbrcpsych</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Royal College of Psychiatrists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4495831</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/pb.bp.114.048215</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Papers</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Heads in the sand may leave old age psychiatry looking foolish and vulnerable</article-title><subtitle>Commentary on . . . A memory clinic <italic>v.</italic> traditional community mental health team service</subtitle></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>David</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>PSSRU, The University of Manchester</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp>Correspondence to David Jolley (<email>David.jolley@manchester.ac.uk</email>)
</corresp><fn><p><bold>David Jolley</bold> is a consultant psychiatrist and honorary reader at the PSSRU, The University of Manchester.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>12</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>6</month><year>2014</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 The Author</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article published by the Royal College of Psychiatrists and distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="12.pdf"/><abstract><p id="P1">Dementia has been recognised as a major challenge to health, social care and economies. Research by Rubinsztein and colleagues, in this issue, has compared the services provided by memory clinics with those of traditional community mental health team services. They conclude that memory clinics offer a more comprehensive and multidisciplinary service at no extra cost. Here I will question some of their findings and highlight the importance of better continuity of care between primary and secondary services.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2">These are heady times for the dementia lobby. London&#x02019;s G8 Conference on dementia was the latest in a series of national and international &#x02018;think-ins&#x02019; that has seen the condition emerge from the shadows of denial and neglect to be recognised as the single most significant challenge to health and social care, economies and personal philosophy now and for the predictable future.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup></p><p id="P3"><italic>The Guardian</italic>&#x02019;s letters page and a thoughtful article from Richard Ashcroft laid bare the realities of our situation.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> Awareness of dementia has been improved, but are services being made available to help people affected by it and are the research initiatives producing better lives and reducing stress associated with the condition? Richard Ashcroft&#x02019;s mother-in-law received a diagnosis and was discharged after two contacts by &#x02018;old age psychiatry&#x02019;, leaving her, her family and general practitioner to feel left adrift in a sea made no-less frightening by having acquired a label.</p><sec id="S1"><title>Rubinsztein <italic>et al</italic>&#x02019;s research</title><p id="P4">Judy Rubinsztein and her colleagues<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> provide an interesting and important description and analysis of what happens when someone with a memory problem is referred by primary care for specialist assessment and advice. They compare the experiences and costs associated with a memory clinic, the model that has become the Holy Grail of assessment through the National Dementia Strategy,<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> and assessment with less formality by a community mental health team (CMHT). Referral rates were similar: 5 per 1000 of the over 64-year-old population per annum. The CMHT patients were older, they were less impaired and were seen more quickly after referral. The diagnostic spectra were similar. Neither service was bedevilled by a long waiting list such as is described by many floundering services.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Stakeholders were happy with both systems but measures that equate quality with assessment by more than one profession, and make use of formalised paper protocols and checklists, prefer the memory clinic model: memory clinic patients were twice as likely to receive a copy of the letter summarising the findings and plans for their future care.</p><p id="P5">The increased &#x02018;quality&#x02019; attributed to the memory clinic is said to be achieved at no greater, actually lesser, cost. Yet, we might wonder how useful all those paper scaled measures are and many will question the costings: digging deeper we find that half of patients referred to the CMHT service were seen only once, and by a consultant in their own homes. The paper judges this to be poor practice, yet this is not reflected in stakeholder views. It might alternatively be viewed as an elegant and efficient approach that reserves multidisciplinary assessments at the clinic, which are time-consuming, less convenient and more costly for patients and carers, for people with more complex presentations. The memory clinic model might be construed as:
&#x02018;one-size-fits-all&#x02019; with everyone attending the clinic, 22/33 having two to six contacts. This is the sort of consideration that makes people question the advantages of clinic-based services. The differential that deems the CMHT model more expensive relates exclusively to travel costs, where the high salary of consultants who are travelling and one outlier who was visited eleven times, load the CMHT pricing. This is a brave and important attempt to capture costs and relate these to activities and effectiveness. It leaves us to reflect how difficult a task this is.</p><p id="P6">The paper opens a fascinating window on what actually happens in this world of dementia care. A total of 35% per cent of people &#x02018;eligible&#x02019; for cholinesterase inhibitors did not receive them. This is the reality and gives a degree of balance to criticism of the UK for its relatively low rate of prescribing these substances:<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> even when assessed, not every patient will accept such treatment, others will encounter side-effects or become disabused. One wonders what is happening in those countries that report prescriptions to near 100% of the predicted prevalence of Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease.</p><p id="P7">Three CMHT patients (10%) were retained for further care, but only 1 of 33 in the memory clinic was directed to their CMHT. One patient (out of 66) received cognitive stimulation therapy and three saw a neuropsychologist. The memory clinic is applauded for &#x02018;signposting&#x02019; more patients to other services: third sector, social services or benefits. Overall, Richard Ashcroft might be forgiven for feeling that not much of substance is evident after the initial flurry.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Identifying weakness in existing services</title><p id="P8">The arguments in favour of including specialist memory services within the spectrum offered by old age psychiatry and other disciplines are strong, cogent and widely accepted.<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup> With great respect, however, both models described here are failing. Their referral rates are such that they cannot close the gap that still exists between predicted prevalence and diagnosed prevalence.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref></sup> There is no increase in referrals associated with the memory clinic arrangement, nor are the patients seen by that clinic earlier in the course of their dementia (as measured using the Mini-Mental State Examination). Tellingly, neither makes a tangible contribution to the continuity of care that patients, families and colleagues in other agencies respect and expect.</p><p id="P9">Variations that simply replace doctors with cheaper nurses, rate per hour<sup><xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref></sup> may not be more cost-effective. They are more likely to rely on standardised protocols with inclusion/exclusion criteria designed to be risk-avoidant and limit workload rather than respond to patient need.<sup><xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> Lessons from the 10/66 studies and initiatives encourage the use of low-tech, clinically competent approaches with training and support to local healthcare agents.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup></p><p id="P10">In countries with established large populations of older people, including the UK, the realisation is that we must bring specialist skills into primary care so that people with dementia can be assessed, treated and supported by a competent local team that knows them as whole people with multiple strengths and multiple weaknesses associated with a range of pathologies.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref></sup> Models that do this achieve referral rates more than twice those reported in East Anglia, sustain patients, carers and primary care colleagues throughout the journey of dementia and other frailties before death, and reduce expenditure on secondary health care.<sup><xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref></sup></p><p id="P11">Despite the rhetoric of &#x02018;war on dementia&#x02019;, and exposure of the myth of the dependency ratio,<sup><xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref></sup> actual service support for older people, including those with dementia, has been reduced by 30% in this country.<sup><xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr">19</xref></sup> Populist politicians are given column space to stir up unjustifiable resentment against old people.<sup><xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr">20</xref></sup></p><p id="P12">Psychiatrists and their colleagues need to remain clear-headed, open and honest as advocates and providers for people with dementia and their families. We are learning what works and is affordable and this is what matters.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="S3"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="P13">Rubinsztein and her colleagues have done us good service in dissecting and comparing the innards of clinic-based and community-based memory services. They have answered some questions and opened others to be pursued, which is all to the good; but we must lift our heads from the sand of what we have been doing within the comfort and discomfort of secondary care to work across the false border that is assumed between primary care and secondary care. There is little to be gained from a well-made diagnosis unless it is part of a meaningful, continuing process of care for the patient and their caring family.</p></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Declaration of interest</bold> None.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>G8 dementia Summit 2013</source>. <publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name>, <year>2013</year>
<comment>(<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-dementia-summit">www.gov.uk/government/news/g8-dementia-summit</uri>)</comment>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Guardian</collab>. <article-title>No magic bullet for dementia</article-title>. <source>Guardian</source>
<year>2013</year>; <day>13</day>
<month>12</month>: <fpage>39</fpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ashcroft</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Dementia delusions</article-title>. <source>Guardian</source>
<year>2013</year>; <day>13</day>
<month>12</month>: <fpage>36</fpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rubinsztein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>van Rensburg</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Al-Salihy</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Girling</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafortune</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Radhakrishnan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>A memory clinic v traditional community mental health team service: comparison of costs and quality</article-title>. <source>Psychiatr Bull</source>
<year>2014</year>; <comment>doi: 10.1192/pb.bp.114.048215</comment>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>Living Well with Dementia</source>. <publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name>, <year>2009</year>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Memory clinics under pressure, NHS England dementia lead admits</article-title>. <source>Pulse</source>
<year>2013</year>; <day>13</day>
<month>9</month>
<comment>(<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.pulsetoday.co.uk/clinical/therapy-areas/mental-health/memory-clinics-under-pressure-nhs-england-dementia-lead-admits/20004307.article.U3ryh5UU_IU)">www.pulsetoday.co.uk/clinical/therapy-areas/mental-health/memory-clinics-under-pressure-nhs-england-dementia-lead-admits/20004307.article.U3ryh5UU_IU)</uri>.</comment>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bond</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stave</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Sganga</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Connell</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanley</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Inequalities in dementia care across Europe: key finding of the facing Dementia survey</article-title>. <source>Int J Clin Pract</source>
<year>2005</year>; <volume>59</volume> (<issue>supplement 146</issue>): <fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Moniz-Cook</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Memory clinics in context</article-title>. <source>Indian J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>51</volume>: <fpage>70</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<collab>Department of Health</collab>. <source>Dementia: A State of the Nation Report on Dementia Care and Support in England</source>. <publisher-name>Department of Health</publisher-name>, <year>2013</year>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Duffin</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Nurse-led clinics set to improve dementia care in England</article-title>. <source>Nurs Older People</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>5</fpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Hope</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Maj</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Mathew</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Doing things differently &#x02013; working towards distributed responsibility within memory assessment services</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>280</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21472781</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shaji</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Smitha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lal</surname><given-names>KP</given-names></name><name><surname>Prince</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Caregivers for Alzheimer&#x02019;s disease: a qualitative study from the Indian 10/66 2 Dementia Research Network</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>
<year>2003</year>; <volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12497550</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>The 10/66 Dementia Research Group</collab>. <article-title>Care arrangements for people with dementia in developing countries</article-title>. <source>Int J Geriatr Psychiatry</source>
<year>2004</year>; <volume>19</volume>: <fpage>170</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14758582</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Hillier</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Stolee</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Heckman</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gagnon</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>McAiney</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Enhancing dementia care: a primary care-based memory clinic</article-title>. <source>J Am Geriatr Soc</source>
<year>2010</year>; <volume>58</volume>: <fpage>2197</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>204</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20977435</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Meeuwsen</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Melis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Der Aa</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Gol&#x000fc;ke-Willemse</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>De Leest</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Raak</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Effectiveness of dementia follow-up by memory clinics or general practitioners: randomized controlled trial</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>344</volume>: <fpage>e3086</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22589500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greening</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Positive thinking on dementia in primary care: Gnosall Memory Clinic</article-title>. <source>Community Pract</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>82</volume>: <fpage>20</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19480115</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreland</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Greaves</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Jolley</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Putting personalisation and integration into practice in primary care</article-title>. <source>J Integr Care</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spijker</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>MacInnes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Population ageing: the time-bomb which isn&#x02019;t</article-title>. <source>BMJ</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>347</volume>: <fpage>f6598</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24222481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Age</surname><given-names>UK</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>Care in Crisis</source>. <publisher-name>Age UK</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>
<comment>(<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.ageuk.org.uk/Documents/EN-GB/Campaigns/CIC/Care_in_Crisis_report_2014.pdf?dtrk=true">www.ageuk.org.uk/Documents/EN-GB/Campaigns/CIC/Care_in_Crisis_report_2014.pdf?dtrk = true</uri>)</comment>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Huhne</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Someone needs to fight the selfish short-sighted old</article-title>. <source>Guardian</source>
<year>2013</year>; <day>23</day>
<month>12</month>.
</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>