<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="book-review"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pbrcpsych</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Royal College of Psychiatrists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4706206</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/pb.bp.114.047845</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Columns</subject><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Reviews</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Mindfulness for Health: A Practical Guide to Relieving Pain, Reducing Stress and Restoring Wellbeing</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ernst</surname><given-names>Thomas A.</given-names><prefix>Dr</prefix></name></contrib></contrib-group><author-notes><fn><p><bold>Dr Thomas A. Ernst</bold> FRCP, Department of Ageing and Health, Guy's and St Thomas' Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust, London, UK, email: <email>thomas.ernst@gstt.nhs.uk</email></p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage seq="a">320</fpage><lpage>320</lpage><product><name><surname>Burch</surname><given-names>Vidyamala</given-names></name><comment> and </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><name><surname>Penman</surname><given-names>Danny</given-names></name><x>. </x><publisher-name>Piatkus</publisher-name><comment>, </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><year>2013</year><comment>, </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><comment>&#x000a3;12.50</comment><x>. </x><comment>, pb, </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><comment>288 pp</comment><comment>. ISBN: </comment><x>&#x000a0;</x><isbn>9780749959241</isbn><x>. </x></product><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 The Author</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article published by the Royal College of Psychiatrists and distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="320.pdf"/></article-meta></front><body><p id="P2">This book leads the reader through a journey of how to deal with suffering from bodily symptoms-related illness and injury. It clearly describes the differences between primary suffering due to injury and secondary suffering largely created within the mind through learnt views, behaviours and fears the person has experienced in their life or through their illness. It then gently describes how, by engaging with the secondary suffering, much of the suffering can be relieved or brought down to the primary pain and suffering which is generally easier to manage within traditional medicine. The book also points out that traditional medical models of pain often miss secondary suffering, whereas traditional therapies often fail to address secondary suffering or can even make it worse. It is to the great credit of authors that they deal with this sensitive issue with compassion and empathy.</p><p id="P3">The book then turns into a step-by-step practical guide on how to approach secondary pain and suffering. The guide is complete with audio recordings of practices that the reader can easily follow and this will not require excessive time. Real-life experiences of people who were helped by following this guide are included.</p><p id="P4">The problem of dealing with pain and suffering is as old as humanity and the readers would have come across many hopes and promises made by medicine, alternative medicine and the spiritual sector among others. This book outlines not only anecdotal evidence in the form of testimonies from people engaging in mindfulness but also benefits from a wealth of research which it refers to.</p><p id="P5">As a doctor having used mindfulness successfully to manage my own pain and suffering from illness, I found reading this book was somewhat challenging, as it would be to many other readers. However, I have not yet read a book on mindfulness so sensitive and gentle with the issue of pain and suffering as this one.</p></body></article>