<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pbrcpsych</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Royal College of Psychiatrists</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4706217</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/pb.bp.114.050013</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Special Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>YouTube and &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019;</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gordon</surname><given-names>Robert</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>John</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>Noel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="A3">3</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="A1"><label>1</label>University Hospital Southampton NHS Foundation Trust, Southampton</aff><aff id="A2"><label>2</label>Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain (Masters student)</aff><aff id="A3"><label>3</label>Surrey and Borders Partnership NHS Foundation Trust, Godalming</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">
Correspondence to Noel Collins (<email>noel.collins@sabp.nhs.uk</email>)
</corresp><fn><p><bold>Robert Gordon</bold> is a CT2 psychiatric trainee in the Wessex Deanery and an academic clinical fellow in psychiatry at the Academic Centre of College Keep, Southampton, <bold>John Miller</bold> is a Masters student at the Universidad Complutense de Madrid, Spain, <bold>Noel Collins</bold> is an older adult consultant psychiatrist at Surrey and Borders NHS Foundation Trust, Godalming.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>39</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>287</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>28</day><month>10</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>27</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>2</day><month>3</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 The Authors</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0"><license-p>This is an open-access article published by the Royal College of Psychiatrists and distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="285.pdf"/><abstract><p id="P2">YouTube is a video-sharing website that is increasingly used to share and disseminate health-related information, particularly among younger people. There are reports that social media sites, such as YouTube, are being used to communicate an anti-psychiatry message but this has never been confirmed in any published analysis of YouTube clip content. This descriptive study revealed that the representation of &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; during summer 2012 was predominantly negative. A subsequent smaller re-analysis suggests that the negative portrayal of &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; on YouTube is a stable phenomenon. The significance of this and how it could be addressed are discussed.</p></abstract></article-meta></front><body><p id="P3">YouTube (<uri xlink:href="www.youtube.com">www.youtube.com</uri>) is a video-sharing website created in 2005, which now provides a platform for 2 billion clip viewings every day.<sup><xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">1</xref></sup> The website's viewership statistics are eye opening. More than 1 billion unique users visit YouTube each month. Over 6 billion hours of video content are watched each month and 100 hours of video are uploaded to YouTube every minute. It is available in 61 countries and across 61 languages, and according to Nielsen, YouTube reaches more US adults aged 18-34 than any cable network.<sup><xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref></sup></p><p id="P4">Clip content is varied, uncontrolled and often anonymous. Whereas clips are uploaded and accessed by diverse individuals, groups and political bodies across the globe, universal access is restricted in some countries. In China, for example, YouTube access was blocked by the government in 2009 as a response to Tibetan content.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> YouTube website administrators also reserve the right to remove uploaded content should users violate specified terms and conditions. Video files that ignite social political unrest, violate copyright and intellectual property protection laws, or breach national security legislation are likely to be removed. According to the YouTube terms of service, material which is obscene, defamatory or unlawful must not be submitted.<sup><xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref></sup> Despite these restrictions, the YouTube platform is largely an unregulated medium which is being used to circulate extraordinarily varied material. This includes sharing and disseminating health-related information, particularly among younger people.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> Against this backdrop, there is growing concern that internet social media are being increasingly used to communicate an anti-psychiatry message.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> However, to our knowledge, this has never been confirmed in any published systematic analysis of YouTube content. This descriptive study aimed to determine whether YouTube portrayed &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; in a positive, neutral or negative light. In view of the enormity of the viewership statistics, we consider the implications of this.</p><sec id="S1"><title>Study</title><p id="P5">On 12 July 2012 we examined YouTube on default search settings using the solitary search term &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019;. We believed this to be the most appropriate description of the discipline as a whole and the most likely reductionist YouTube search term for the specialty. Other possible search terms such as &#x02018;mental health&#x02019; were discounted owing to the conceptual overlap with psychopathology and other constructs and the likelihood of generating broad and irrelevant search results. YouTube ranks search results according to relevance gained from the title of the clip, descriptive language within &#x02018;relevant keywords&#x02019; and &#x02018;video tags&#x02019;, and the video description itself. Furthermore, the higher the number of &#x02018;comments&#x02019; a video possesses, the higher the &#x02018;authority signal&#x02019; becomes (i.e. the inherent video popularity, which also promotes a higher ranking).<sup><xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">8</xref></sup></p><p id="P6">The first 100 clips of more than 1000 ranked results were viewed independently by two researchers (R.G. and J.M.) and categorised as positive, negative or neutral in their representation of psychiatry. No explicit criteria were used in categorising clips, which were assigned to each category according to the global impression of reviewer regarding the overall theme of each clip. Clips were assigned &#x02018;neutral&#x02019; as a default if no overall negative or positive theme was identified. Disagreements in clip category were arbitrated by a third reviewer (N.C.). The number of views and clip length were also recorded. Non-functioning, deleted or repeated clips were excluded from analysis. Browser software at the time of examination was up to date and there was no disagreement between non-functioning clips observed on different computers.</p></sec><sec id="S2"><title>Study results</title><p id="P7">The kappa agreement between observers was 76%. The observers excluded 20 clips from analysis. The majority of eligible clips portrayed psychiatry negatively (51%) compared with neutrally (29%) and positively (20%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">Table 1</xref>). Negative clips were viewed more frequently and were longer than both positive and neutral clips. A subsequent smaller re-analysis of the first ten ranked clips on 14 July 2013 (five negative, two positive, three neutral) and 13 August 2014 (six negative, one positive, three neutral) revealed similar findings. A selection of analysed clips is provided in <xref ref-type="boxed-text" rid="box1">Box 1</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of negative, positive and neutral clips on 12 July 2012</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="center" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="center" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="center" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clip type</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eligible clips,<break/><italic>n</italic> (%)</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average number<break/>of clips views</th><th valign="bottom" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average clip<break/>length</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Negative</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">41 (51)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77 035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14m 49s</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16 (20)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">54 234</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9m 34s</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" rowspan="1"><hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Neutral</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 (29)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7244</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7m 20s</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p id="P8">Common themes of negative clips related to the process of diagnosis and treatment. In particular, psychiatric diagnoses were criticised for being invalid, unreliable and a non-scientific mechanism of social control. Other concerns included stigma and the &#x02018;labelling&#x02019; of individuals with diagnoses, administering toxic psychotropic medication to children and the potential harm of psychiatric treatment. Themes of positive clips included the benefits of psychiatric research, improvements in treatment and an anti-stigma video (&#x02018;Beards and Bowties&#x02019; by Dr Kamran Ahmed: <uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=70loMcIqd9Q">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=70loMcIqd9Q</uri>). Neutrally themed clips were largely educational in nature, including a cartoon portrayal of the proposed neurotransmitter mechanism of bipolar affective disorder.</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="S3"><title>Discussion</title><p id="P9">This study reveals that the representation of &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; on YouTube in July 2012 was predominantly negative. Subsequent clip analyses in 2013 and 2014 suggest that this is a stable phenomenon. The source of negative YouTube clips was unclear owing to blind authorship. However, there were three &#x02018;regularly negative&#x02019; authors of clips promoting a seemingly &#x02018;anti-psychiatry&#x02019; campaign.</p><p id="P10">What does a search term of &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; mean? Content analysis of clips suggested the discipline of psychiatry itself was the implied meaning of &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; in the majority of clips. Although other medical specialties also suffer from negative portrayals on YouTube, this is usually topic-specific such as paediatric immunisation or objections to tanning by dermatologists.<sup><xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>-<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref></sup> &#x02018;Psychiatry&#x02019; as a medical discipline appears uniquely targeted on YouTube for negative representation.</p><p id="P11">Why is portrayal of psychiatry on YouTube negative? The YouTube medium itself is vulnerable to extreme content owing to blind authorship, presentation of opinion as fact and the distinct lack of any peer review or editorial process.<sup><xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref></sup> The online anti-psychiatry campaign has been linked to Scientology, disgruntled patients and psychiatrists, critical social scientists, humanistic psychologists and journalists sceptical towards psychiatry.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> It has also been suggested that an anti-psychiatry group now exists as a patient-based consumer movement.<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> This online antipsychiatry message may be increasing,<sup><xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref></sup> with the release of DSM-5 being a particular nidus of further criticism.<sup><xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref></sup> The negative online representation of &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; may also be an extension of long-standing societal scepticism of &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; into a contemporary medium. It could also be symptomatic of the overall failure of psychiatry to promote itself more positively.</p><p id="P12">It is unclear whether information disseminated through social media platforms influences health-related attitudes and behaviours.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> More educated viewers appear relatively resistant to inaccurate information on YouTube, even when the message is framed as scientific reasoning.<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> However, it does appear that social media websites are becoming an increasingly popular source of health information.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> The spiralling volume of uncensored information being uploaded to social video platforms such as YouTube makes it difficult for heath consumers to discern reliable health information from misleading content. Certain patient groups, such as younger adults and people with anorexia, may be more vulnerable to extreme content.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> It is also unclear how the negative online representation of psychiatry interacts with real-world stigma surrounding psychiatric illness and its treatment.</p><boxed-text id="box1" position="float" orientation="portrait"><p id="P13"><bold>Box 1</bold> A selection of clips from the original 2012 analysis</p><p id="P14"><bold>Negative:</bold></p><p id="P15"><uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y_AC-JhPOI">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y_AC-JhPOI</uri> (The psychiatric drugging of children &#x00026; elderly)</p><p id="P16"><uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hy79C0v8elE">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=hy79C0v8elE</uri> (Psychiatry)</p><p id="P17"><uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PcuhhJ1BaMk">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PcuhhJ1BaMk</uri> (The DSM: psychiatry's deadliest scam)</p><p id="P18"><bold>Positive:</bold></p><p id="P19"><uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dFs9WO2B8uI">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dFs9WO2B8uI</uri> (RSA animate &#x02013; the divided brain)</p><p id="P20"><uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tTCwihayOv0">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tTCwihayOv0</uri> (Peggy Rodriguez, MD for UNM Department of Psychiatry Residency Program)</p><p id="P21"><uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=89-LDCnP8qw">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=89-LDCnP8qw</uri> (Anthony Rothschild, MD: Brudnick Chair &#x00026; professor of psychiatry)</p><p id="P22"><bold>Neutral:</bold></p><p id="P23"><uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5N8LJjGjsfI">http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5N8LJjGjsfI</uri> (Ask the doctor: cardiology, psychiatry, geriatric medicine)</p><p id="P24"><uri xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qVkYHioCHpk">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qVkYHioCHpk</uri> (Psychiatry, Ain Shams University, basic interviewing skills 1.wmv)</p><p id="P25"><uri xlink:href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jq5F2XRt6QM">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jq5F2XRt6QM</uri> (Psychiatrist vs psychologist (mental health guru))</p></boxed-text><p id="P26">Despite negative representation, viewing rates of YouTube &#x02018;psychiatry clips&#x02019; are low compared with other content. The most popular &#x02018;psychiatry&#x02019; clip, a music video by The Avalanches entitled &#x02018;Frontier psychiatrist&#x02019;, including a parody of the psychotherapist and patient encounter, attracted 2.3 million views. To give some perspective, &#x02018;Gangham Style&#x02019;, a music video by the South Korean musician Psy, attracted 1.5 billion views, &#x02018;Charlie bit my finger again&#x02019; 520 million and the Taiwanese &#x02018;Nyan cat&#x02019; animation 101 million views.</p><p id="P27">Although the effects of negative representations of psychiatry on social media remain questionable, it is clear that YouTube content is capable of exerting global impact. Sceptics of this need only heed the story of Sonya the slow loris. In 2009, Dmitry Sergeyev uploaded a video of her being tickled. Although illegal to have a captive slow loris as a pet outside of Russia, this single viral video has increased the illegal pet trade of these animals and has now led to the near extinction of the species.<sup><xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref></sup></p><sec id="S4"><title>Psychiatry fighting back</title><p id="P28">Accepting that negative representation of psychiatry on YouTube is a concern, how can it be addressed? Psychiatrists, their professional bodies and healthcare providers could start by recognising the influence of social media and its potential for disseminating health information, particularly in younger health consumers.<sup><xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref></sup> Promisingly, the Royal College of Psychiatrists has launched its own YouTube channel (<uri xlink:href="www.youtube.com/user/RCofPsychiatrists">www.youtube.com/user/RCofPsychiatrists</uri>). This currently has low impact, with its introductory clip displaying a modest (2000) number of views, but it could eventually be a platform to provide unbiased and accurate information and to convey a positive message about psychiatry more generally. It may be as important to raise awareness among younger people and vulnerable patient groups about the trustworthiness of online information more generally.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> Others have suggested political leverage on YouTube to communicate more objective information<sup><xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref></sup> or to carry explicit disclaimers when an extreme view is represented (in the same manner as television). Further options include the development of algorithms to automatically detect and filter extreme videos before they become popular.<sup><xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref></sup> However, these proposals are somewhat at odds with the overarching YouTube ethos of free &#x02018;self-broadcast&#x02019;.</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Declaration of interest</bold> None.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><p id="P29">The authors thank Alberto Pavanello for his advice and encouragement throughout.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Springer</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Social media &#x02013; risk management</article-title>. <source>Plast Surg Nurs</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>32</volume>: <fpage>22</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22395173</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>YouTube</collab></person-group>
<source>Statistics</source>. <publisher-name>YouTube</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year> (<uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/yt/press/statistics.html">http://www.youtube.com/yt/press/statistics.html</uri>).
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Helft</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>YouTube blocked in China, Google says</article-title>. <source>New York Times</source>, <day>24</day>
<month>3</month>
<year>2009</year>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>YouTube</collab></person-group>
<source>Community Guidelines</source> (<uri xlink:href="http://www.youtube.com/yt/policyandsafety/communityguidelines.html#communityguidelines-line-crossing">http://www.youtube.com/yt/policyandsafety/communityguidelines.html#communityguidelines-line-crossing</uri>).
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vance</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Howe</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Dellavalle</surname><given-names>RP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Social internet sites as a source of public health information</article-title>. <source>Dermatol Clin</source>
<year>2009</year>; <volume>27</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19254656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robichaud</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawken</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Beard</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morra</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<article-title>Vaccine-critical videos on YouTube and their impact on medical students' attitudes about seasonal influenza immunization: a pre and post study</article-title>. <source>Vaccine</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>30</volume>: <fpage>3763</fpage>-<lpage>70</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22484293</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitley</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>The antipsychiatry movement: dead, diminishing, or developing?</article-title>
<source>Psychiatr Serv</source>
<year>2012</year>; <volume>63</volume>: <fpage>1039</fpage>-<lpage>41</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23032676</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kaushal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group>
<source>How to make your videos rank better on YouTube</source>. <publisher-name>ClickZ</publisher-name>
<year>2014</year>, <day>23</day>
<month>6</month> (<uri xlink:href="http://www.clickz.com/clickz/column/2351591/how-to-make-your-videos-rank-better-on-youtube">http://www.clickz.com/clickz/column/2351591/how-to-make-your-videos-rank-better-on-youtube</uri>).
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keelan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pavri-Garcia</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomlinson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>YouTube as a source of information on immunization: a content analysis</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<year>2007</year>; <volume>298</volume>: <fpage>2482</fpage>-<lpage>4</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18056901</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ache</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Human papillomavirus vaccination coverage on YouTube</article-title>. <source>Am J Prev Med</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>35</volume>: <fpage>389</fpage>-<lpage>92</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18675530</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hossler</surname><given-names>EW</given-names></name><name><surname>Conroy</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>YouTube as a source of information on tanning bed use</article-title>. <source>Arch Dermatol</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>144</volume>: <fpage>1395</fpage>-<lpage>6</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18936411</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bourgeois</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>A storm is brewing around the DSM V (the new antipsychiatry) [in French]</article-title>. <source>L'Encephale</source>
<year>2014</year>; <volume>40</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>-<lpage>2</lpage>.
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hayanga</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Medical information on YouTube</article-title>. <source>JAMA</source>
<year>2008</year>; <volume>299</volume>: <fpage>1424</fpage>-<lpage>5</lpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18364483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nekaris</surname><given-names>KA-I</given-names></name><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Coggins</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Rode</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nijman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<article-title>Tickled to death: analysing public perceptions of &#x02018;cute&#x02019; videos of threatened species (slow lorises &#x02013; Nycticebus spp.) on Web 2.0 sites</article-title>. <source>PloS ONE</source>
<year>2013</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e69215</fpage>.
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23894432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>