<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="book-review">    <?properties open_access?>    <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?>    <?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?>    <?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?>    <?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?>    <?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?>    <?ConverterInfo.Version 2?>
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">pbrcpsych</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn>
            <issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>Royal College of Psychiatrists</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4495826</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/pb.bp.114.047126</article-id>
            <article-categories>
                <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                    <subject>Columns</subject>
                    <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
                        <subject>Reviews</subject>
                    </subj-group>
                </subj-group>
            </article-categories>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Our Encounters with Self-Harm</article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group>
                <contrib contrib-type="author">
                    <name>
                        <surname>Hunt</surname>
                        <given-names>Elizabeth J. F.</given-names>
                    </name>
                </contrib>
            </contrib-group>
            <author-notes>
                <fn>
                    <p>
                        <bold>Elizabeth J. F. Hunt</bold> is ST4 in liaison psychiatry, Department of Psychological Medicine, King&#x02019;s College Hospital, London, UK, email: <email>elizabeth.hunt@slam.nhs.uk</email>
                    </p>
                </fn>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
                <month>2</month>
                <year>2015</year>
            </pub-date>
            <volume>39</volume>
            <issue>1</issue>
            <fpage seq="b">54</fpage>
            <lpage>55</lpage>
            <product xlink:type="simple">
                <source>Our Encounters with Self-Harm</source>
                <comment> Edited by </comment>
                <x>&#x000a0;</x>
                <name>
                    <surname>Baker</surname>
                    <given-names>Charley</given-names>
                </name>
                <comment>, </comment>
                <x>&#x000a0;</x>
                <name>
                    <surname>Shaw</surname>
                    <given-names>Clare</given-names>
                </name>
                <comment> and </comment>
                <x>&#x000a0;</x>
                <name>
                    <surname>Biley</surname>
                    <given-names>Fran</given-names>
                </name>
                <x>. </x>
                <publisher-name>PCCS Books</publisher-name>
                <comment>, </comment>
                <x>&#x000a0;</x>
                <year>2013</year>
                <comment>, </comment>
                <x>&#x000a0;</x>
                <comment>&#x000a3;18.00</comment>
                <x>. </x>
                <comment>, </comment>
                <x>&#x000a0;</x>
                <comment>pb, 229 pp.</comment>
                <comment> ISBN: </comment>
                <x>&#x000a0;</x>
                <isbn>9781906254636</isbn>
                <x>. </x>
            </product>
            <permissions>
                <copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 The Author</copyright-statement>
                <copyright-year>2014</copyright-year>
                <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                    <license-p>This is an open-access article published by the Royal College of Psychiatrists and distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0</uri>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p>
                </license>
            </permissions>
            <self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="54.pdf" />
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <fig id="F1" position="float">
            <graphic xlink:href="54f2" />
        </fig>
        <p id="P1">When I was working as a junior doctor in accident and emergency, one of my favourite jobs was suturing. A pleasant break from the constant decision-making, an opportunity to do something practical and almost artistic, and most of all a chance to just sit down and chat with the patient as I stitched. Despite this, one of my least favourite tasks was patching up those who had self-harmed. Something about the sight of the self-inflicted wounds upset me far more than the most horrendous accidental injuries; I tried to still be warm and not allow the distress and disgust I felt show, but I did not know what to say and we would often sit in silence as I worked. I had never been taught about non-suicidal self-harm, what it serves, how to approach it, anything. It was not until I began my psychiatric training that I began to understand it, and became retrospectively frustrated with how I had felt and responded to it earlier in my career. I now ensure I cover this subject in some depth with my medical students, to try to avoid them feeling about self-harm the way that I used to. Alternatively, I could just make them read this book.</p>
        <p id="P2">
            <italic>Our Encounters with Self-Harm</italic> is made up of 37 pithy chapters by different authors. The majority are written by those who have, or still do, self-harm, and others are by family members and professionals (the last of which I found the least educational; an interesting reminder not to dismiss personal accounts in an era where quantitative research often feels the only thing that counts). Most take the form of a piece of prose about the writer&#x02019;s personal experience, followed by a short bullet-point list of thoughts that they would like the reader to take away from it.</p>
        <p id="P3">These pieces are brave, articulate, occasionally harrowing, and frequently illuminating. Since it is an anthology, unsurprisingly there is a certain amount of repetition within the book. This is no complaint; it serves to reinforce the most common themes such as: accept that this is my coping mechanism, find out what it means to me, look beyond the act of self-harm to treat the person behind it with kindness. Meanwhile, the divergences remind us of other key points such as not making assumptions and remembering that &#x02018;everyone who self-harms is an individual, so everyone&#x02019;s self-harm has individual meaning&#x02019;.</p>
        <p id="P4">Buy this book and force every medical and nursing student you encounter to read a chapter from it. I suspect it would significantly improve in the future the care that patients presenting to accident and emergency with self-harm receive. While you are at it, share it with your psychiatric colleagues; a reminder of empathy and a deepening of our understanding of our patients can never go amiss. As one of the contributors writes, &#x02018;whatever you learn, get it out there, you never know who might benefit from your own experiences&#x02019;.</p>
    </body>
</article>