<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BJB</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6465223</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjb.2018.92</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S205646941800092X</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00092</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Even more against the stream</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Correspondence</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Correspondence</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>Lachlan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Consultant Psychiatrist</addr-line>, <institution>Blackfriars Medico-Legal Consultancy</institution>, <addr-line>London</addr-line>, <country>UK</country>; email: <email>lach2929@googlemail.com</email></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>42</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage seq="a">266</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2018</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is unaltered and is properly cited. The written permission of Cambridge University Press must be obtained for commercial re-use or in order to create a derivative work.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S205646941800092Xa.pdf"/><counts><page-count count="1"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>We all know the law is an ass, but when it comes to defining an age of consent it is more like a badly assembled chimera. You can become criminally responsible at the age of 8 or 10, liable to criminal prosecution from the age of 12, legitimately have sex at the age of 14 while on holiday in Germany, join the Army at 16 and perhaps later die for your country, vote and purchase alcohol or cigarettes at the age of 18, but not hire a car until the age of 25. What an Alice in Wonderland world we live in! Logic would suggest a similar age for all of these activities, perhaps with some allowance for variation justifiable by the extent of risk involved.</p><p>The appropriate legal age of sexual consent is not immediately obvious. However, as sexual intercourse with a child under the age of 13 amounts to statutory rape, this might provide a logical starting point. Incidentally, when I last checked, the lowest age of sexual consent in a European country was actually 12 (in Vatican City, somewhat ironically).</p><p>Of course, in reality, the limited availability of parliamentary time will make a logical alignment of the various ages for consent a complete non-starter. So perhaps a better question is &#x02018;Why have an age of consent at all?&#x02019; This allegedly offers protection but in reality mainly just criminalises a substantial proportion of the juvenile population and potentially even criminalises an underage victim of a sexual assault. Surely criminal responsibility should only rest with the perpetrator? In this scenario, a perpetrator would commit a crime if, and only if, a sexual act occurred in the absence of consent, and not simply by reason of some arbitrary age. Can we not trust our children to reach their own decisions and just make consent, or rather lack of consent, the sole reason for engaging criminal law?</p></body></article>