<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="letter"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BJB</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6048727</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjb.2018.35</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2056469418000359</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00035</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Correspondence</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Unlocking an acute psychiatric ward: open doors, absent patients?</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Correspondence</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Correspondence</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>Damian</given-names></name><role>Senior Registrar in General Adult Psychiatry and Clinical Tutor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>McCauley</surname><given-names>MacDara</given-names></name><role>Consultant Psychiatrist and Clinical Lecturer</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><institution>Louth Meath Mental Health Services and Royal College of Surgeons Ireland</institution>; email: <email>damiansmith@rcsi.com</email></aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>6</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>42</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>132</fpage><lpage>133</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Authors 2018</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution licence (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S2056469418000359a.pdf"/><counts><ref-count count="5"/><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>In their recent paper, Beaglehole and colleagues<xref rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr"><sup>1</sup></xref> reported on the effects of unlocking an acute psychiatric ward. Despite a 58% increase in unauthorised absences and an 8% increase in violent incidents, they concluded that a less restrictive environment had some positive effects, most notably a reduction in the total hours of seclusion per month.</p><p>Our service has recently undertaken a similar transition from a locked acute ward opened (and locked) in the 1930s, to an unlocked newly built unit opened in 2016. When comparing the 6 months before and after this transition, we too found that the rate of unauthorised absences increased by 100% from a mean of 4 to 8 per month. Unlike Beaglehole, however, we observed a decrease in rates of violent incidents by 27.4% (from a mean of 31.7 to 23 per month), and an increase in the total hours of seclusion per month by 213.4% (from a mean of 28.21 to 88.42 hours per month). Of note, admission rates increased from a mean of 20 to 23 per month during the same time period.</p><p>Although a reduction in the rate of violent incidents (and, in the case of Beaglehole, reduced levels of seclusion) strengthens the case for provision of care in unlocked settings, should we be concerned about the increased rate of unauthorised absences found in both studies?</p><p>The largest available study on this topic<xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr"><sup>2</sup></xref> would suggest not. In their 15-year observational study involving 145,738 German in-patients, Huber <italic>et al</italic> concluded that locked doors do not prevent suicides, or indeed unauthorised absences.</p><p>Although a rare event, suicide is undoubtedly one the most feared outcomes when any patient absconds. Preventing harm to self or others is often the main rationale for in-patient admission. It is also a ubiquitous criterion for involuntary admission. Consequently, preventing harm is one of the main motives for locking psychiatric units.</p><p>In our study, 86% of unauthorised absences over the 1-year study period were by involuntarily admitted patients. In opening our doors, are we doing these individuals a disservice by giving them the opportunity to leave hospital at a time when they are most unwell?</p><p>Previous studies have reported on the negative consequences of absconding for patients (interrupted treatment, suicide), staff (anxiety), family members (loss of trust in the service), and emergency services (expended resources).<xref rid="ref3" ref-type="bibr"><sup>3</sup></xref> It could be argued that a reduction in the number of violent incidents (and, in Beaglehole's case, seclusion) is worth the risk of these adverse outcomes. In our view, however, a modern purpose-built environment coupled with increased staffing levels better explains these findings. Increased numbers of nursing staff result in improved relational security, an important element of therapeutic security provided by higher staff-to-patient ratios.<xref rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr"><sup>4</sup></xref></p><p>Our study and that of Beaglehole and colleagues indicate that unlocking acute psychiatric wards leads to an upsurge in unauthorised absences. The majority of patients who absconded were admitted involuntarily. We suggest that acute mental health services give careful consideration to all the risks associated with unauthorised absences before opening their doors. This is of particular relevance given that rates of involuntary admission are on the rise.<xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr"><sup>5</sup></xref></p></body><back><ref-list id="reflist1"><ref id="ref1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beaglehole</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beveridge</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Campbell-Trotter</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frampton</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Unlocking an acute psychiatric ward: the impact on unauthorised absences, assaults and seclusions</article-title>. <source>BJPsych Bull</source>
<year>2017</year>; <volume>41</volume>: <fpage>92</fpage>&#x02013;6.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28400967</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneeberger</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kowalinski</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fr&#x000f6;hlich</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Felten von</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal/>
<article-title>Suicide risk and absconding in psychiatric hospitals with and without open door policies: a 15 year, observational study</article-title>. <source>Lancet Psychiatry</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>3</volume>: <fpage>842</fpage>&#x02013;9.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27477886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Page</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ndimande</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Connell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vincent</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Absconding: reducing failure to return in adult mental health wards</article-title>. <source>BMJ Qual Improv Rep</source>
<year>2016</year>; <volume>5</volume>: u209837.w5117.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>HG.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Therapeutic uses of security: mapping forensic mental health services by stratifying risk</article-title>. <source>Adv Psychiatr Treat</source>
<year>2002</year>; <volume>8</volume>: <fpage>433</fpage>&#x02013;43.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ref5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gilhooley</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>BD.</given-names></name>
<article-title>Return of the asylum</article-title>. <source>Br J Psychiatry</source>
<year>2018</year>; <volume>212</volume>: <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>70</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29436325</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>