<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="obituary"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">BJPsych Bull</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">BJB</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>BJPsych Bulletin</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2056-4694</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2056-4708</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6001871</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1192/bjb.2017.21</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pii">S2056469417000213</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">00021</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Obituary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Joan Bicknell</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running">Obituary</alt-title><alt-title alt-title-type="right-running">Obituary</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hollins</surname><given-names>Sheila</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>2</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>42</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>48</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author 2018</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Author</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p><!--CREATIVE COMMONS-->This is an Open Access article, distributed under the terms of the
Creative Commons Attribution licence
(<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted
re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original
work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:title="pdf" xlink:href="S2056469417000213a.pdf"/><counts><fig-count count="1"/><page-count count="2"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Dorothy Joan Bicknell, psychiatrist, born 10 April 1939; died 12 June 2017</p><p>
<fig id="fig01" orientation="portrait" position="float"><caption><p>Brilliant clinician who was appointed professor of psychiatry of learning
disability at St George's, University of London.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="S2056469417000213_fig1"/></fig>
</p><p>In 1980, Joan Bicknell, who has died aged 78 of cancer, was appointed professor of
psychiatry of learning disability &#x02013; the first British female professor of psychiatry &#x02013;
at what is now St George's, University of London. A brilliant clinician, she put the
disabled person and their family at the centre of each consultation.</p><p>She was in constant demand to speak to trainees, parent groups and learning disability
services about her vision of what could be done, and published dozens of papers for both
clinicians and families. An article drawn from her inaugural lecture as a professor in
1981, The Psychopathology of Handicap, was published in the journal Psychological
Medicine, and remains inspirational today.</p><p>In it, she described the emotional effect on parents and siblings of the diagnosis of
learning disability in the family and also explored what it is like for children and
adults living with a learning disability in terms of their own emotional inner world,
their expectations for adulthood and the extent to which they were included or excluded
from participating in daily life in the community. At the time, most people with
learning disabilities lived at home with their families &#x02013; unless the family could no
longer support the person &#x02013; and the alternative was usually a hospital admission.</p><p>Joan demonstrated that with specialist advice, community services could provide families
with more support to care for longer, and the growing number of community homes and
hostels could be supported to provide family-style care. This was unpopular with many
medical superintendents of &#x0201c;mental handicap&#x0201d; hospitals, and she was never accepted by
the medical establishment.</p><p>In 1978, a public inquiry into a scandal at Normansfield hospital in Teddington,
south-west London, found the medical leadership seriously at fault. The nurses at
Normansfield had gone on strike two years earlier complaining about how dysfunctional
the organisation was, and the appalling conditions in which people with learning
disabilities were living. The South West Thames regional health authority accepted the
inquiry recommendations and appointed Joan to lead a taskforce to transform the care
provided. It brought staff and relatives together to create an improvement plan, a new
multidisciplinary management structure was put in place and money was provided to build
more accommodation to reduce overcrowding.</p><p>It was against this background that Joan became professor, heading a new NHS-funded
academic department to launch the specialty of psychiatry of learning disability at St
George's, covering south-west London, Surrey, Sussex and Hampshire. St George's remains
a leader in teaching medical students how to communicate effectively with people with
learning disabilities, work that began in 1982, when Joan started involving her patients
and their families in face-to-face teaching.</p><p>During her working day she met patients and families in the clinic or at home, supervised
trainees, advised NHS and social service managers and fielded phone calls from people
seeking advice. In the evenings and at weekends she would be booked as a speaker or for
consultations all over Britain. She took early retirement in 1990 at the age of 50,
having suffered from mental illness and severe asthma for the final three years of her
career.</p><p>Perhaps the hardest thing for her to deal with had been the failure of NHS managers and
of politicians to respond with meaningful action when she spoke up for the human rights
of people with learning disabilities. She wrote in the Personal View column for the
British Medical Journal about the men in a locked ward who were not allowed access to
the kitchen or to drinking water and resorted to filling their shoes with water from the
lavatory pan. Eventually a water fountain was installed in the living room, only for it
to be blocked up by staff using it to dispose of their cigarette ash. Confronting
cruelty in such hospitals was yet another of the ways she contributed to the advance of
enlightened disability psychotherapy and psychiatry.</p><p>Born in Isleworth, south-west London, Joan lived in the capital for most of the second
world war with her mother, Dorothy (nee Smith), a solicitor's secretary and later a
foster parent, and her older brother, Edward, who went on to become a teacher in
Swaziland, where he later died. Her father, Albert Bicknell, a foreman bricklayer in
peacetime, served with the Royal Engineers in bomb disposal.</p><p>From Twickenham County school for girls Joan went to Birmingham University, graduating in
medicine in 1962. A Methodist missionary society needed a paediatrician urgently at the
Ilesha Wesley Guild hospital in Oyo, Nigeria, so Joan interrupted her paediatric
training to test her new medical skills in a very different setting. When the Biafran
war began in 1967, Joan was rounded up with others at bayonet point and put on a plane
to Sierra Leone. There she worked on the flying doctor service before returning home.</p><p>She took a post at Queen Mary's hospital, Carshalton, in Surrey, where her concern about
the poor care given to severely disabled children was strengthened by her own family
experience, when her mother fostered two brothers with learning disabilities. This was
the new challenge she needed and five more years of clinical training followed.</p><p>Joan obtained the diploma in psychological medicine in 1969, and in 1971 completed an MD
on the causes and prevalence of lead poisoning in institutionalised children. She was
soon active in campaigning about the restricted and poorly supported lives that people
experienced in long-stay hospitals.</p><p>In 1972 Joan became a consultant psychiatrist in mental handicap at Botley's Park
hospital, Chertsey, where she later met Diane Worsley, a social worker. Their friendship
and partnership stood the test of time, and after Joan retired they moved to Holnest,
Dorset, and ran a farm, welcoming disabled children to work with the animals. Joan and
Diane also built up the Longburton Methodist chapel, where they were worship leaders. In
2016 they sold the farm and moved to nearby Stalbridge.</p><p>The community team base at Springfield University hospital in Tooting, south-west London,
where Joan did much of her pioneering clinical work, was named after her when she left.
The Royal College of Psychiatrists instituted an annual essay prize in her honour.</p><p>She is survived by Diane.</p></body><back><notes notes-type="other" id="nts1"><p>This article has been reproduced with kind permission from <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://theguardian.com">theguardian.com</uri>.</p></notes></back></article>